Josh communicated but
it's also the belief that
we never knew the severity
nor I don't think he knew how to
communicate the severity of it.
I had a pretty happy childhood
You know, I had trouble fitting
in but nothing outside the norm.
The night before ninth grade
started, I broke down crying.
I struggled a lot with these
feelings that
I didn't know what to do with.
I was sad, I had no energy.
I eventually was diagnosed with
depression.
I started hurting myself.
I cut and did other forms of
self-harm
and I thought about suicide.
When I was 12, I started
feeling depressed.
I was sitting in the car on
my way to a girl scout event
and someone mentioned a book
about a girl who
had committed suicide,
and I think that's the moment
that I realized that,
that's what I wanted to do.
There was a magazine in a
doctor's office,
that had an article about
kids having cutting groups
and going to the
bathroom and cutting
and I thought, I could try this
and it just became an addiction
because when I was nervous or
anxious or depressed or angry
that's what I would go to.
In my past, I've had experience
with eating disorders,
suicide, and self-harm.
As far as eating disorders
go, there was a time when I
deliberately withheld food from
myself in order to lose weight.
Self-harm, for about a year
and half straight I would
wake up in the morning with
a knife under my pillow
and cut myself on my arm
and my inner leg.
There were a couple of
times when I attempted to
commit suicide by cutting
myself and bleeding out.
When I was 13, I began to
struggle with
anorexia and depression
and it continued well into
the age of 17.
When I was 13, nearly 14
I had reached the first stage
of my weight loss plan, which
was to achieve 98 pounds.
I wanted to break 100 pounds
'cause anything more than that
seemed obese.
[Sarah] I remember I would
constantly check my weight
on online
calculators for B. M. I.
to make sure that I was under
16.8 which was considered to be
underweight by all standards
and I thought that was an
accomplishment
so I kept it as close to that
as I could
and wanted to go even lower.
I had a fantastic childhood,
it's always hard to talk about
this most of the time with
people, or to feel legitimacy in
the struggles that I went
through because I hear a lot of
people who said that they were
abused as children and had
really rough childhoods
but I had... um...
a great upbringing, supportive
parents, great family life.
There was nothing was nothing in
my life situation
that should have pointed to the
struggles that I encountered,
particularly with depression but
it started to become
something that was beyond
my control
by the time that I reached 13
it kind of snuck up on me.
Again a Fairfield Township
family
is struggling for answers
tonight
after the untimely death of
their daughter.
Florida authorities believe a 12
year old girl
committed suicide.
A community is mourning the
suicide of a 13 year old
who took his life at school.
Harleydonna McGuire whom
everyone called "Kitty"
committed suicide last Tuesday.
A mother found her ten year old
daughter
who had committed suicide.
A new government report showed
an 8% increase in suicides among
children and young adults
and that is the largest rise in
about 15 years.
[Matt]
We see these stories every day.
Depression, anxiety, eating
disorders, self-harm
these are just a few of the
prominent mental illnesses that
teens and young adults face.
For many young people, these
conditions are an unexplained,
confusing, and often paralyzing
part of their lives.
[Sarah] They can grow
to believe
that this is
their fault.
That this is something
they should be ashamed of.
Sometimes they're too afraid
to reach out for help.
Sometimes they're pressured to
hide this part of them away.
[Narrator] We started this
project as a small group
of high school and
college students
to tell our own stories and
those of our close
friends and family.
We have seen first hand how easy
it is to hide behind a mask.
We wanted to start a
conversation.
We put out a call asking for
teens to share
their experiences with us
and were amazed at the
response we received.
Our crew expanded shooting
hundreds of hours of footage.
We saw the effect the stigmas
had on the
lives of countless
teens.
These are the stories we wanted
to tell.
I was in my mid-twenties,
I had a good job, I was you
know... I kind of...
I called it my mask life.
Everyone on the outside
would think I was doing fine.
I had a good job, I had a lot of
friends,
I was involved in things
on the inside I was miserable,
and I really didn't share that
with anybody
because I didn't trust
anybody enough to do that.
I was content in my life,
there was no reason why
I would
be unhappy.
But there were these symptoms
that started to kind of overtake
the way that I viewed myself,
and also my future, and it was
uncharacteristic
because I always was, and have
tried to be a very happy person,
very positive and optimistic and
that's what people knew me as.
So when I started to feel off,
I didn't know how to
explain it to anyone
I didn't know how to understand
it myself
so I just didn't talk
about it
and that was when I was 13.
When I was depressed,
I think my self-esteem got worse
cause everyone
was telling me that I should
have been okay,
and I was trying to be
and I couldn't be and I felt
like a failure
in that I couldn't do anything
right.
And I remember sitting in my
apartment,
at a window seat on
the third floor
looking down, and I
really really considered
jumping out the window that
night.
I remember
that night vividly.
I have had issues with
depression
and cutting from when I was a
freshman in
high school up until my
freshman year of college.
I first started struggling with
depression
when I was about
10 or 11 years old.
I brought that with me into
college where things got worse
because, you know, I was
separated from my family,
my academic standards became...
sort of... just a cloud,
constantly hanging over me.
It got to the point where I was
cutting pretty much every day.
In her book "The Bell Jar",
Sylvia Plath talks about the
idea that
depression and mental health
issues can act like a bell jar
in which, it can descend at any
moment and you're trapped.
There's the world outside, and
there's you inside and
everything is distorted,
everything is suffocating and...
and I'm still trying to work
through that.
I was in middle school, so I
didn't really realize that
I could have killed myself
accidentally with cutting.
I never really thought about it,
I just liked the pain and the
release.
[Laurel] I was talking to a
girl 'til two...
three in the morning
who was cutting that night
and I just said "How do you know
that the cuts that you make
might not be the one that takes
your life?"
You know, I mean she wasn't in a
suicidal mode that night.
She was just trying to release
some pain.
And I said "How do you know?
How do you cross that line,
or know that you're not
going to cross that line?"
And the fear was so real,
she was just like
"I don't want to kill myself
tonight,"
"I just want the pain to stop
and go away."
and you know, your heart aches
for that
because it is a real fear.
They know that, there's no
parent
is going to be really excited to
say
"Oh terrific" you know, yeah.
There's the fear of the
reaction.
Are they gonna scream?
Are they gonna cry?
Are they gonna care at all?
I think that's a
really valid fear
for some of these kids
who feel that no one cares.
They would see the evidence
They would see that
I was upset
and that, you know,
I wasn't doing well
and they would make
comments like
"You know, you seem really
out of it.
are you sure nothing's wrong?"
and I would make it obvious
that I wasn't okay
but they never followed up.
They never... they never
really checked on me.
And then they would see a scar
and they would ask where it
came from and
I wouldn't really answer them
and they would just let it go.
And they would notice that I
wasn't eating and they'd be like
"Have you eaten? Have you
eaten?"
and I'd be like "No, I'll get
there.
I'll eat eventually" and they...
they knew, they just didn't do
anything.
There are clear cut, clear cut
definite situations where a
parent...
parent's lack of
care and concern
would definitely
cross that line.
Especially if, God forbid,
the child ended up
taking their own life.
Ignoring suicide
threats or self-abuse
can be seen as a form of neglect
but I think it becomes
situational.
There are some kids that go to
such extreme lengths to hide,
especially self-abuse,
that the parent
really isn't aware.
The best thing that we can
possibly do
is to help them find
ways to cope
where they are, in the
situation they're in
and for some it's two,
three, four, five years
that they have to go through
until they can walk out the door
and make a life.
There's nothing better than
seeing a kid
that has done that,
that has made it.
You know? And that has said
"I chose this path and I'm
really, really glad."
For the early part of fall,
I knew nothing of
Annie's condition.
In November, on finding her
blog, I was thrown into a world
that affects me even today.
Posts showing graphic images
of self-harm
composed almost all of it.
[Anonymous friend]
I remember being horrified
that I could be
so ignorant
of so much pain being
so near to me.
What really strikes me
in the community
that I'm involved with is
just how much kids are trying
desperately to save the lives
and be there for their friends.
My parents still, they didn't
understand
and I'm not sure if
they were trying
or if they just didn't want to,
but I needed the help
that I wasn't getting.
I was introduced to Annie
through a mutual friend,
they asked if I could act sort
of as a lifeline for Annie.
For an extended period of time,
literally months,
we would be up until 2 or 3 a.m.
sometimes on a given night
talking with Annie, and you know
trying to talk her down and
we didn't know if she was
going to, you know,
we didn't know if that next
message would ever come in.
We were terrified that she
could literally, you know,
make a decision to end her life
mid-conversation
and we were afraid that
we were helpless.
I wasn't anywhere near
ready to take on
such an emotionally, mentally,
and even physically
demanding role.
Being a support system
took me straight past my limits
as a 15 year old.
I know a couple of kids that
have been there for others,
and one of the things
I am also stressing to them,
and I think this is
so important:
Yes, it's important to
love the person,
and yes it's important...
they need that.
They need to know that
somebody's there.
They've got my back. They're
gonna never leave me.
They're gonna always love me.
But that person needs to set
boundaries
and take care of
themselves as well.
The stress and accountability
was almost unbearable.
It got to the point where
I was terrified to sleep
and terrified that on waking
I'd find out that she dead
and all because I hadn't stayed
up to talk to her.
I had no experience, no
training,
no reference to go by.
Yes, you need to be there
but you also need to
take care of yourself
because you can't be that friend
if it's all give, give, give,
give and you're not getting
anything back for yourself.
Someone had told my mom
that they thought that
I was just looking for attention
and that what I was going
through wasn't real.
If there someone who is looking
for attention,
there's obviously a reason for
that,
and just going through
depression,
it's not for attention, it's...
You can't do anything about it,
it's just there.
In Annie's case, she was
obviously in need
far before she
received professional help.
But between family strains
and receiving devoted
non-professional help
it doesn't surprise me that she
only received help
when the matter was unavoidable.
I think my parents felt that
they didn't want anything to be
wrong with me
so that they didn't raise a
child who was messed up.
They just... They didn't want to
accept
the fact that I wasn't okay.
[Annie] A friend of mine
called the cops,
around the time that I was 14
because I had told him that I
was going to kill myself
and when the cops showed up,
I told them that nothing
was wrong,
and my parents told them that
nothing was wrong.
It just felt like no one wanted
to deal with what was going on.
The first night of 2011,
I stayed up very late
into the night,
talking to a friend about Annie,
which was only to set the theme
for the next months to come.
Nearly every night would find me
either talking to her
desperately
or talking to another friend,
completely at a loss for
what to do.
The worst part was our seeming
utter lack of progress.
I would go to bed one night,
somewhat assured that my long
conversation with her
had made some impact,
yet the next night she would
be as bad as ever.
She needed us.
That much was clear.
She had a date.
The seventh, because
seven is a good number.
I remember asking a friend
what that even meant,
yet not even pausing for an
answer.
She had a place,
the creek by her house.
The rawness of how concrete
her intentions were
almost destroyed me.
After dealing with weeks of
"I'm going to kill myself"
here she was,
and she was ready despite
everything we gave.
...and everyone was frantic,
you could tell that these people
loved this person so much.
So I hopped in my car and
I drove to the hospital,
and it's like, I had no idea if
the parents were even going to
let her see me,
or if the parents would
let me in, but I was like
"I have to go, and find out what
I can."
Just to let the network of
support know what's going on,
because there were so many
that were there that cared.
[Annie] When I was at the
emergency room,
I had two different doctors come
in and ask me questions and
I... I was still scared,
I didn't want to tell them
the date.
I didn't want them to know it
was something that,
I felt maybe I could still get
away with I guess?
And after a little while they
told me and my mom
that I would have to be
hospitalized.
I've had that person tell me
what that visit meant.
You know, I was only there for
about five minutes.
Both parents were there
so it was very, very awkward.
Um.
And that we couldn't
really talk at all.
But that person has
repeatedly told me
that just having me
show up that night
and know that all those
people were asking,
it made a huge difference.
And I think that's really what
it amounts to,
it's having that
support network that
if your family can't give
it to you,
then you find the family that
can.
I know a lot of people in
my life struggle with depression
and anxiety and self-harm,
and all of those situations are
different,
but a lot of times I feel like
they aren't supported by
their families.
I don't really think I would
have wanted
my parents in particular
involved.
I think my parents were kind of
emotionally in-equipped to help.
Somebody, maybe other parents
I knew,
were probably more helpful and
influential than my own,
I think at times, but no I
don't think
having my parents involved would
have helped.
One night, I was on the verge
of attempting suicide
and somebody knew about it
and called my parents.
My parents didn't come in
and check on me,
they didn't say anything,
they didn't...
they didn't even say anything
the next day, like...
They didn't do anything.
Even when all of those things
were brought
directly to
their attention.
The lowest point that I have
ever reached in my life was when
I was sitting right at
this kitchen table actually,
many of the people who I had
invested in, in the past,
who I had identified myself
as a savior figure unhealthily,
their situations began to take
a downward spiral
and there was nothing
that I could do to help them,
and by some twist of fate,
it all happened at once.
I remember sitting here being
so unable to come to terms
with the fact that I needed
to move on
and I needed
to find something
else to focus on because
that's what I had told
so many other people
when I was counseling
them as a friend,
that when they had reached
this point,
you just have to focus
on the positive.
And that hit home
especially hard because
I was the one who was supposed
to be the positive figure.
So when I couldn't
do that myself,
it was the scariest feeling.
[Sarah]
I remember sitting here,
allowing all of these things to
consume me,
and I felt so drowned by them.
I thought that this was some
sign from the universe that
my purpose was done here.
If I removed myself from the
world,
that it would be a greater gain
than if I was here.
So I went into the other room
and I got out the painkillers,
and I had done my research,
at that point.
I laid out the exact amount
that I needed.
And I remember staring at them
feeling like...
Feeling this very odd,
unnerving, sense of peace.
That this was again, necessary
for what needed to happen.
Then I went into the kitchen,
and I got a glass of water,
and I set it down, and I
stared at all of it
in front of me,
and got a burst of what some
people may call courage,
and I grabbed on to the first
round of them and
I don't know how
to describe it,
but I was hit with
this feeling of
"Oh my gosh,
what am I doing?"
It was this odd
wave of blankness
in my mind and I
dropped the pills,
I dropped my water
and I just...
I realized at that point that I
needed to finally ask for help
because I never reached
a point that low before
and I had never imagined that
the things that I
considered to be
so necessary for my perfection
and my worth...
They could lead me to such
a dark place.
I think my parents did
want the best for me.
I think they did
want me to recover.
But they didn't know what to do.
And they didn't want to believe
it was as much of
an issue as it was.
I think one of the reasons I
never asked for help
was just... shame.
I didn't feel like I
should need help
to deal with those
kinds of issues and
I didn't... I didn't really want
to involve anyone
other than myself.
I never told my parents
about this
until after I could come to
terms with it myself.
I wanted to be able to have
it all together
in a responsible-sounding
package
before I could discuss it
with them because
to me I was afraid that they
would see it as weakness
and I wanted their trust
because for so long
I had been their confidant.
So, in my mind, the only
way to maintain that
was just keeping it a secret
until I could fix it myself.
One afternoon I was walking to
the school bus
and I had a voicemail
from my dad,
just saying how much he loved me
and cared about me
and when I got home, my mom sat
me down and told me that the
guidance counselor told her I'd
been having a rough time,
and was taking it out in some
pretty self-destructive ways.
At first they handled it by
trying to talk to me.
But I didn't stop right away
and so they tried to punish me.
Threatening to take away things
like time with friends,
or activities that I wanted to
do
if I didn't stop hurting myself.
I think that generally when a
parent
finds out that their child is
suffering from depression or
self-harming, they...
they like to think that it's
just a phase,
that it's not a real issue, that
it's something that they can
ignore because they don't want
to face it.
Nobody wants to face that their
child is
unhappy and hurting themselves.
But it happens,
and it happens a lot more than
we would like to admit.
They punished me by saying
"You can't go to summer camp."
"You can't go to the concert.
You can't hang out with your
friends."
I think they thought it was
something
they could just treat like that.
I don't think they understood
how big the issue was, or what
the issue was.
The issue wasn't that I was
hurting myself.
The issue was that I was so
upset and so depressed
that I restored to hurting
myself,
because I didn't feel like I
could talk to anyone.
You know, when a kid is
depressed you have to wonder why
a parent just doesn't seem to
see it.
So you wonder like "Why?"
Why do the parent's just not
address it.
I think in some cases it really
truly is a case of ignorance.
They really truly may not see
it.
They're just living on a
superficial level and they don't
process what they're seeing as
what it really is.
There are times where I find a
student that
the issues have been brought to
their parents attention.
The parents are refusing help,
appropriate help,
through normal channels
of say therapy
and counseling, and it's always
difficult
because you can't push too much
with a parent that's resistant.
But there are some parents that
really do know.
Their child has been pretty
upfront
that I really, really need
help.
And they're not doing anything,
or they're giving it the
lightest treatment or "It'll
blow over" kind of an attitude.
Then it's getting really close
that line I think of
I don't know if I would call it
abuse but definitely neglect.
A kid who is, you know, 14, 15
years old who is screaming out
for "I need treatment, I need...
I need antidepressants,
I need something." and their
parent's aren't just saying
"It'll pass, it'll pass."
You know, what's going to happen
to that parent if that child
doesn't get the help
they need and they
finally take their own life. I
think of it that way, it's like
then okay, were you responsible
for your child's death?
This isn't talking about the
parents who are just
haven't noticed or... This is
talking about the people that
the kids have come to them or an
educator or someone has come
to them and said "This is what's
going on and it's..."
"You know, there needs to be
something done."
I think a lot of parents take it
personally.
They might take it as an insult
on their...
their own parenting skills.
They might be afraid, again in
previous generations
mental-illness was not
discussed.
It was a matter of shame,
something to be hidden.
And it's really important, I
think, right now to change
that attitude in today's
parents.
To understand that you would
treat a mental illness
the same way you would
treat another illness.
You wouldn't keep
a diabetic home
and not give them insulin
because you're embarrased.
I think there are also a lot of
parents that are
afraid to admit their kid has a
real problem
and is that going to reflect on
my parenting skills,
and the image of what are
people going think if I tell
people my kid is self-harming.
Are they gonna think
that I'm a bad parent? So it's
easier just to ignore it.
Maybe it'll go away, maybe
they'll get over it.
It's okay to be honest, it's
okay to talk about this stuff.
If you struggle, if you struggle
with depression or addiction
it shouldn't be any different
than a broken arm,
or the flu, or even cancer. You
know, those are things that
if you were sick in that way or
you broke a bone
you wouldn't try to hide it, you
wouldn't try to play it off.
And we... And yet when it comes
to mental health so many people
do try to hide it, and so many
people feel like they
can't talk about it, and we want
to be about seeing that change.
I'm always trying to get the
kids to look at it from
the parent's point of view as
well.
Only in that they have to
understand that
the parent's might be doing the
best that they can do.
They don't know what kind of
baggage their parents have
brought into the situation.
Were they abused as kids?
Did they have alcoholism
involved?
There's always another story
that they might not be
taking the time to see.
I think a lot of times we have a
problem with things
that we don't understand. And
so that's outside
our comfort zone and we tend to
avoid it or we tend not to
go there, and I'm not a parent
but I can imagine that as a
parent it's a difficult thing to
be honest about the fact
that your son or daughter is
struggling, and maybe they
feel like that's a reflection on
them.
I think sometimes it's easier to
sidestep it,
pretend you don't see it. You
know, yeah he's a teenager
he's just got a bad attitude.
It's not about being a teenager
and having a bad attitude, it's
about being a teenager
and you being his mom or dad,
and you need to pay attention
to know what's going on in your
house.
We buy into the idea that our
friends, our family,
they're busy, they have problems
of their own.
They have enough on their plate.
And as a result I think
sometimes we think we're
supposed to just get through our
stuff on our own.
You know we're supposed to
toughen up or suck it up
and there's a lot of lies that I
think make up that stigma.
I know in the black community,
getting help for mental health
isn't really something that is
done.
When I was a senior in high
school I went to see a...
a psychologist, because I was
stressed and anxious
and depressed. Instead of going
to therapy
my mother had suggested, you
know like,
"I think that you can deal with
this on your own,
I think you'll be fine without
therapy, without drugs" and
Looking back now, I wish I had
gone to therapy
instead of trying to deal with
it on my own
and struggling with it for so
long.
If you were afraid to talk to
your parents you were supposed
to speak to a teacher or a
guidance counselor
that you trusted, which I did in
a very round about way.
I just said "You know, I'm
having some trouble
with these mood swings. I'm not
sure what to do."
One way or another it got back
to my parents and they were
less than supportive. They
thought that I was being
overdramatic and that I was
vying for attention and that
all I needed to do was "Get my
head on straight, work harder."
and uh.... So I...
When I had a chance to get help,
I kind of caved
and said "You're right, I'm
sorry, I don't mean
to cause trouble. I'll shut up
now." It was a mistake.
It's a parent's primary
responsibility to protect
their child.
If they have even an inkling
that there might be
something wrong, I would suggest
that you err
on the side of caution.
Please get help. If it turns out
it's nothing, well thank God,
and if it turns out it's
something then
you may have just saved that
kid's life.
Everyone knows somebody that's
taken their life,
there's no question and I
remember in college
I remember getting the news that
somebody had taken their life,
and it was somebody I never
would have expected
would kill themselves.
And so, again it gets back to
that whole mask, you know.
Like you can appear like
everything's fine
and inside you're just dying. So
you know, you just have to...
You have to meet people where
they are, but if there are
visible signs, you just, you
have to...
I'm amazed at the people that
can just turn away,
and say, you know, "I don't want
to get involved."
Maybe they're afraid to get
involved?
Maybe they're afraid they don't
know how to deal with it?
I don't know.
-[Jim] Suicide, as
anyone grew up I mean...
-[Laurette] You didn't
talk about it.
-[Jim] You didn't talk about it.
You were to be, that was a...
-[Laurette] It's a big secret.
-[Jim] That was a....
It was an embarrassment to the
family if you lost somebody
due to suicide. It was a... you
were a coward if you
committed suicide. Those are all
the things I remember
um, about suicide.
I remember back in school, and I
went to a huge high school,
one kid in the four years I was
there committed suicide.
It was not something that... and
we were stunned
because no one did that.
So I think, that is part of it.
Suicide has become
much more culturally
accepted in teens as
almost the final coping
strategy,
or lack of being able to cope.
I remember for the next week
after she had committed suicide,
I just kind of walked around in
a fog.
I remember writing a poem about
it, and you know
the empty chair in the room and
the dust, and like...
What happened?
Where did that girl go?
And I remember at graduation a
couple years later,
she would have been sitting next
to me alphabetically,
we were in the same major.
And I remember when they called
the name
of the person that was right
before me I was thinking
she should be next.
She should be walking up to get
her diploma right now.
For a long time I felt like
there was something
not right with my body and
everyone would say
"Oh you're fine, you're just
feeling a little sad," or
"Oh your problems aren't that
real like you just have to
get over it or just don't think
about it too much."
and it was when I came to
college that I actually
finally did something about it.
And I wish I had done something
about it earlier, at least like
seek the help that I knew I
needed.
Maybe it starts with being
honest with a friend or
a family member and we end up
sounding like a broken record.
[Jamie]Encouraging people
to talk to a counselor
to step into treatment.
To take that next step in the
direction of professional help.
I think the biggest challenge is
the stigma because
we've learned that it's
something
people are afraid to talk about,
and so I think that's
the biggest thing we're up
against is that idea
that people buy into
where they say
"Oh, this is something
I can't say out loud.
This is a part of my story
that no one should know.
This is a question I've never
asked." This is...
This is... something that goes
far beyond the status update
and the pictures that we...
we post.
You know, kind of the...
the stories that we're
comfortable with
in terms of our own lives.
-Laurette I think that kids feel
that they have to keep
it a secret because...
Um...
"Oh my God, somebody's going to
find out that... I have all this
stuff going on in my head and I
don't know what to do with it.
You know, what are they
gonna think of me?
What are my friends gonna
think of me?"
I think in some cases,
Josh was that guy.
Um...
He was... a star football
player.
I mean, he was um...
a really good looking kid.
He had many, many friends.
None of my friends knew during
the time of my
depression and
anorexia of
anything that I
was struggling with.
I didn't let them. I didn't let
them into my world
to really
know what was
honestly and truly going on with
me because I was afraid
of what they would think of me.
I was helping many people
who were struggling
with similar things and I didn't
want them to know that I was
dealing with the same issues
because I thought that would
discount my desire to be there
for them.
There was no...
that I knew of... counseling.
There was no hotline that I
could call. Um...
Other than seeing what was
derogatorily
referred to as a shrink.
So far as I know, there was no
such thing as a support system.
Maybe it existed, um...
But I didn't have access to it.
They want the pain to end,
but they don't...
They're afraid to
find other alternatives.
I think that's why suicide
is so rampant is that
they desperately, desperately
want the pain to end
but they don't know to find
other ways to make that happen.
Or they feel trapped
before that can happen.
And so it's just an alternative
that...
They feel like it's the
only answer.
I was just too intimated.
I felt like I was the only
person in the world
who was ever having
this kind of trouble and um...
I didn't want embarrass my
parents.
I didn't want to put anyone out.
You know, I'm a...
I come from a large family um...
so anyone causing trouble for...
You know, causing trouble for
one of us obviously
causes trouble
for the whole family.
So um.. I wish that I had...
had the courage to stand up for
myself and say "You know,
Yes. I need help.
Please take me to a doctor."
But I didn't then.
The statistic that really
has stayed with me over
the years was the one that said
that two out of three people
who struggle with depression
never get help for it.
That most people who need help
never even take that first step.
Most people never put
a hand up and say
"Hey, I'm not doing well,
I need help."
And so I think we've come to
believe that
so many people struggle alone.
So many people feel alone
when it comes to their
pain or their questions.
And uh...
And so I think we've had the
amazing opportunity to just
invite people to be honest,
maybe for the first time.
I didn't ask my parents for help
when I was struggling because
I felt like a burden.
I didn't...
I didn't want to be a problem
for them.
Or an additional problem for
them.
I wanted to be...
a perfect daughter.
When I was 14, I began to
develop of
just controlling tinier things.
Um..
It began with my weight. Uh..
This idea of becoming the
perfect version of myself,
overtook the way that I was
viewing my prospects before.
[Sarah] Before it was simple,
before it was just having
friends, engaging in thee people
that I knew.
Embracing my family and
somehow this obsession kind of
overtook all of those priorities
and soon all that I cared about
was how much I weighed.
You know, I think there is a
tremendous stigma, and I think
there's shame and confusion that
kinda hovers over this
conversation and just keeps it
quiet. Keeps it from happening.
And I think we're afraid of
being labeled, we're afraid
of being judged, we're afraid of
being misunderstood.
Most mental illnesses don't
resolve themselves.
It's not a phase.
It's not a bid for attention,
it's not a growing pain.
People need help.
And ignoring a problem doesn't
make it go away,
it makes it much, much worse.
So many people are into
presenting that false, phoney
"Oh yes, we're wonderful, we're
happy,
we do all the right things.
Look at our glorious children
and their
matching outfits and
how wonderful."
It's a bunch of crap.
I mean, it is.
I think a lot of times as
people,
we're afraid of what we don't
understand.
And so we do hear those stories
of young people who don't get
the care that they need and
deserve because
the parents are afraid, or the
parents in a way sweep it
under the rug and say it's not
a big deal.
Or say you know, no, you don't
need that kind of help.
Maybe they even think it's
a reflection on them.
When I came out as bisexual I
had a lot of support from my
friends and I thought that was
enough, but it turns out that
wasn't enough for me.
I feel like there is...
You need to have other friends
who are sort of like you.
And since I came to college I
have more friends that are gay,
bisexual, lesbian and it makes
me not feel so alone.
And I think that is a big part
of depression in LGBT people is
that they might not have a lot
of friends that are similar to
them, or they just feel like
they're alone
I mean, you see... and this
might sound stupid
but I think it's
totally valid.
You see your friends going from
relationship to relationship
and they can hold hands with
their boyfriend or girlfriend
because they're heterosexual
and that's totally fine
and I mean, I feel
like
subconsciously you
sort of think
"Well, if I did that, there's
some risk associated with that."
Or you know like,
it's so much harder
for me to find a
relationship.
Why is it so much harder
for me? And so much
easier for someone else.
Why is it that if I want a
relationship it's so much more
complicated?
It's really confusing, trying to
figure out who you are.
And when who you are can be
condemned by a vast majority of
people around you, that just
makes everything you're going
through so much more difficult.
It makes coping with it that
much harder.
It makes getting help that much
harder because
you're scared to be who you are.
And you're scared to...
You're scared that if you start
unraveling pieces of you
And start showing them to the
world they're gonna condemn you.
Nearly half of transgender
youth have seriously thought
about taking their lives.
One quarter report having
attempted to do so.
Each episode of LGBT
victimization increases the odds
of self-harming behavior
by two and a half times.
In comparison to their straight
peers,
gay, lesbian, and
bisexual youth
are four times more likely to
attempt suicide.
Among these teens, those whose
families reject them are
8.4 times more likely
to attempt suicide.
That means that, compared to
their straight peers,
a teen who is not accepted by
theirvfamily is over 32 times
more likely
to attempt suicide.
I've had friends who've had
problems with
depression, self-harm,
eating disorders
It was actually the way I first
started
making friends in middle
school.
I started hanging out with a
group of girls
and I didn't think anything
different.
like they were great girls,
and we had fun hanging out
and one day we were all called
into the guidance office
together and they asked us to
roll up our sleeves and I was
like "I have no idea what's
going on? I don't understand
why..." I was like
"Okay, I'm gonna do this."
And the other girls
were like, not really,
not really doing
what was asked of them.
One of the girls, after
the initial like
roll-up your
sleeves fiasco
she um... she came to me
and she she was like
'You know what?
This is what I've been doing
like there's marks on my stomach
too,
like it's the only way I
feel better."
And I was like "Well, you know
what? I'm gonna try to help you
anyway I can but I want you to
know that if I can't do
something for you I'm going to
find someone who will."
We're in the seventh grade and
like I was good at keeping
secrets but I wasn't going to
keep a secret that was
gonna hurt someone.
It's not betraying a friend to
go to an adult.
You do not have the tools as a
teenager to be able to handle
something this serious, many
adults don't have the tools.
So go to someone.
Seek out help.
That's being
the best friend you can be.
After the whole guidance
counselor thing
I always prefaced any kind of
conversation that we had like
that with I want you to know
that I will keep your confidence
but the second I feel like I
can't help you,
I will find someone who can.
One of the other ancillary
situations that you deal with a
lot with these children that are
struggling is what to
tell or do
with their friends
because their friends love them,
their friends care about them
but often times they're not
equipped to handle
a friend that's suicidal.
They don't know what to do with
a friend that's cutting, um.
They can... you know,
they're 13, 14, 15 as well.
I didn't know if what I was
doing was right but
I went to the guidance office
like a week later
and she was pulled from school,
the whole
"You have to be evaluated before
you can come back."
And she called me
later that night and told me
I was a terrible friend and that
she would never speak to me
again, she would never trust me
again.
But her mom asked to speak to me
on the phone and
like I didn't know if I was
going to be yelled at?
Like there was that five seconds
of panic where
I was like "Oh no, she's mad at
me and her mom's mad at me
and it's... Is this gonna
be this big thing?"
And her mom, her mom thanked me
for being such a good friend
and that really threw me because
I didn't really...
I didn't understand why she
felt she had to hide this from
her mom if her mom
was thanking me
and I know I didn't know
the whole situation but
she told me that she was proud
of me for going to the
guidance office and talking
to the staff there and
I feel like the
worst part of that was
she never trusted me again,
my friend and
we were never friends
again after that.
[Young Girl]
One in five high school freshmen
will consider suicide this year.
More than any other grade.
Within that class,
girls are
two and a half times
more like than boys
to attempt to end their life.
The suicide rate among 10-14
year olds has grown more than
50% over the last three decades.
Earlier action is essential.
If we start this conversation at
a younger age in schools
and at home, we can prepare
kids to face these topics
as they are entering high
school.
We can do more, we have to do
more.
I think one of the hardest
things for me
to see in all kids that I
work with is
that there are so many that
are really truly in a sense
trapped in their environment.
Most of the kids that I talk to
can be anywhere between
the ages of 12 and
16, 17 years old and because
they're minors the reality
is they're going to be living in
this home for anywhere between
two to five years before they
can walk out the door and
be an adult
and find their own way.
That's really, in the eyes of a
teenager, you know four,
five years is a really,
really long time.
And in the eyes of a depressed
teenager,
it's eons because you just,
you can't see past the pain that
you're in to the fact that
things will get better.
As educators we've discussed
what our role is in trying to
improve the homelife of children
that are having issues.
And it becomes a
very murky situation
because it is really
dependent on each
individual family. There are
some where the people...
The children have gone to such
an extent to hide it,
that just letting the parent
know what's happening
they will be very
proactive, they'll get involved.
They want to try to help.
I had to find the guidance
office on my own,
I didn't know who else to talk
to about it. Nobody...
Nobody knew who to go to.
In some places you have to be 18
before you can get an
antidepressant on your own, or
16 and there's some 14 and
15 year olds that the idea of
four more years of where they
are and what they're living
with, that's like a long,
long time when you're really
feeling depressed.
So if they could go someplace,
and get free counseling,
or if they could go some place
and talk to someone,
that would be huge.
The one thing I do say to kids
who I really think are in a
position where they
could take their life, um...
I think back to when I was in
that really dark place
and I just, I came close and
there's no way in the world at
that point that I could ever
imagine what my life
today would be like,
years and years later.
And I think to myself,
what I would have missed
if I had made that decision out
of that painful moment.
I mean, I would have missed out
on how many years
of incredible happiness,
of joy, of incredible moments,
of people that have
touched my life
and it's just, I sometimes think
that when people
do commit suicide, is the real
tragedy that they then get to
see what they might have missed.
And that, that's what they live
with, for eternity.
Like, oh my God, this is
what I could have had.
-[Jim] We've had no prior
experience with any kind of
depression. No exposure to,
close experience to depression.
So what Josh experienced was
brand spanking new
to us, and uh, you know...
We followed the best advice and
practices we could at the time.
-[Laurette] Started freshman
year of college.
Started experiencing what he
explained as panic attacks.
He just kept saying, you know,
it feels like somebody's
sitting on my chest,
physical pain, and you know,
wound up in the E.R. a couple
times at school.
He would drive four hours every
weekend and come home
from school,
all of freshman year.
He was there what?
-[Jim] Semester.
-[Laurette] First semester. He
was at St. Francis in Altoona
for one semester and was home
every weekend. Just because it
was difficult for
him to be there.
When he was finished with his
freshman year,
or his freshman
first semester
We um... looked into
West Chester
which was not that far away,
and um...
He was there for five hours.
-[Jim] Mhmm.
-[Laurette] We took him down,
unpacked him.
Thought everything
was fine.
Five hours later we got a call
from campus police
that he was
in the hospital.
He had taken too many Xanax,
which was what he thought was
going to help him, you know,
struggling with the anxiety, and
um...
He was in I.C.U. for probably 24
hours. Something like that.
So it kind of all started to
unravel, freshman year,
and then from that point we
brought him home
and had him do online courses.
-[Jim] So we got there and
talked to the doctor
and one of the
comments the doctor
made when he came in was
he felt like a failure.
So this was in the
midst of his stupor and
so when he came out
of it they
actually had a
psychiatrist evaluate him
because he felt the way he did.
And uh, their suggestion
was to take him home for a
couple weeks
and then send him back, well you
can't really do that in college
so we took him home, he got
online schooling, and then we
proceeded to look for a
psychologist and a psychiatrist
for him to talk to,
that lasted probably the next
five or six months he was going
once a week.
Josh communicated but
it's also the belief that
we never knew the severity
nor I don't think he knew how to
communicate the severity of it.
He would communicate,
he would
at times try
to self-medicate
and every time he came out of
that self-medication I call it
he would talk and...
but he never...
I don't want to say he wanted to
be a burden to anybody but
I also don't think he knew
how to fix it.
He didn't, he didn't want to...
he didn't feel comfortable
communicating or he didn't
communicate it
'cause when he did
he couldn't, he couldn't
express it.
-[Laurette] Never one time did
Josh ever say
"I don't want to be here."
Not one time.
-[Laurette] He took his life in
the garden that he made for me
'cause I think he was comforted
by being there.
Josh died February 6th of this
year. Um...
I'll never be the same.
I'll never be the same person.
He'll never be the same.
It's difficult to function
most days
and I think someone
that takes...
is considering
taking their life
you need to understand
what you're leaving.
And when you make that kind
of decision
I know sometimes
I hear people say
"It's like something snapped
in them and they just did it."
Josh talked to me that night.
He said "Mom, you know
I've been thinking about it all
all day today." and I was like
"You know what Josh?
We'll put a plan together.
We will do something.
We will go talk to
somebody else.
We will...we'll do whatever
we gotta do
because we get up,
this family gets up.
[Laurette] No matter what,
we will get through it.
We will do what we have to do
and it doesn't matter.
If you're not good tomorrow
we'll figure it out.
And as far as I was concerned
we had it figured out.
Josh could not
be the burden that he... He
didn't want to be a burden to us
and honestly I don't care
who you are.
You're not a burden
to your family ever.
Ever.
We, you know, there wasn't...
There wasn't anything
that we wouldn't have done
because we are
forever changed.
[Laurette] I'm not saying that
we're um...
we're not living because
we're surviving.
That's what we're doing.
And for another parent,
another sister, another brother
to have to do it,
we don't want that.
That's why we're willing to tell
this story to somebody.
I don't want to watch somebody
else do what we're doing.
[Jamie] There's a lot of forms
of brokenness on this planet
that people are okay
talking about
and for some reason
when it comes to depression,
when it comes to self injury
or addiction or suicide
these are things that are often
not talked about and we love
the idea of that changing and
think that honesty is the
beginning, honesty is really
contagious and disarming and
has a way of letting people
know it's okay to go there
and you're not alone
in how you feel.
When you're in the midst of all
of this pain and insecurity
and fear it can be hard to reach
out for help or even have
a conversation with one of
your closest friends about
what's going on in your own mind
and in your own feelings because
it can be hard to value
yourself enough
to receive the
help that you need.
I'm glad I got help when I did
but I wish I had gotten
help sooner
maybe if I had things
wouldn't have gotten so bad.
If I... If any of my children
ever went though something
like that, I would um...
definitely try to be as
emotionally available
and just present as I could to
help them and then also get them
any kind of professional help
that I was able to
so they wouldn't have to
go through it on their own.
I had the privilege of visiting
the White House about a
year and a half ago and was part
of a group of about 150 people
who work in the realm of
mental health and
got to hear from the President
and the Vice President
and all sorts of folks
were there and...
and the day was really meant to
represent and indicate
the idea that things were
changing and that this
is a priority to the leaders of
this country and that it should
be easier, it should be more
comfortable, more accessible
for people to get help.
Even though three quarters of
mental illnesses emerge by the
end of... by the age of 24,
only about half of children with
mental-health problems
receive treatment.
Now think about it,
we wouldn't accept it if
only 40% of Americans with
cancers got treatment.
We wouldn't accept it if only
half of young people with
diabetes got help.
Why should we accept it when it
comes to mental-health?
Doesn't make any sense.
In some cases when a condition
goes untreated it can lead to
tragedy on a larger scale.
We can do something about
stories like these.
In many cases treatment is
available and effective.
The awareness level has to be
higher, it has to be.
There are... We hear it every
day, somebody got bullied
to death or just gave up.
It's an epidemic, it's a very
sad situation
and it's avoidable,
it's preventable.
It can take a few tries
to find something that works
and it's a combination of
professional help, of therapy,
of medication, and even
therapists. Sometimes you don't
click with the first person you
talk to but it doesn't mean it's
not gonna work.
And outside of that, just
finding something in life that
you're passionate about,
something that you can really
work towards. For me that's
photography and music.
If I looked back at myself when
I was 14, when I was depressed
and struggling so much, I think
that girl would see me now and
be amazed at what she's doing.
I'm doing things now that when I
was 14 I wanted to do,
I dreamed of doing, but I never
took the steps to do it when I
was younger because I thought
I couldn't. I've done music
photography and interviews with
people that I never would have
dreamed of, some of the
biggest artists in the world.
People I've looked up to for
years and getting to photograph
these artists just makes
everything come full circle.
Finding my passion really
helped so much.
It gives you something
to work for
and it gives you a reason
to live.
Just know that there are people
around that are gonna support
you and are gonna help you,
you just need to find them
and reach out to them 'cause
there are always people around
that want to be there for you.
That want to help you.
I didn't feel like I had anyone.
I felt completely alone.
I felt like I had no family,
no friends, no support
but looking around
I really did.
I... I had those people
and everyone does.
You're helping them to see that
you're not alone, you have...
And to finally see kids that
have gotten to a point
where they say "My friends are
what saved my life."
You know, "My support system is
That's why we do it.
-[Jim] If you're not doing
anything to help your kid
we would have loved that
opportunity.
-[Laurette] There wasn't...
There wasn't anything...
-[Jim] We don't have that
opportunity anymore.
And if your child's in crisis
and to the point of voluntary
or involuntary treatment,
there should be no other option
because as a parent
It's our belief, we were given
the gift of life with these
children. They are not here for
us.
We are here for them if they
are in crisis of any kind.
It is our responsibility to do
the very best we can
and if somebody comes and...
If one of your children come and
blatantly tell you what
they're thinking.
It is our responsibility as
parents to do everything
possible to get them the help
that they deserve.
I think honesty is contagious
and that so much of it starts
there with just trying to create
environments and relationships
and conversations where people
know that they can be honest
about their struggles and
to stop painting a picture
of this world where everyone's
okay all the time and...
but that we're people and as
people we encounter pain,
we encounter loss,
we encounter depression and it's
okay to be honest about that.
And I think that's how things
maybe begin to change is just
creating an environment where we
go "Hey, if you need help,
it's okay, it's part of
being human.
It's okay to say
you need help.
I know that I will always
struggle with depression.
It's a part of me, but
it is not who I am.
Although it can become
overwhelming some days
and although some days the
symptoms feel like
they're paralyzing me
I've reached out enough to have
people to pull me out from
that place to keep me from going
back into that dark place that
that I reached before, and
although it is a rollercoaster
I know that I will
make it through.
Piano chords
Have you ever been so
far below?
You could only see light using
a telescope
Point it up to the sky and
wonder why does hope
Feel so far, but look
so close?
Will you wander with me
to the edge
Take a breath, tell the world
that we're not finished yet
Cast a net to the stars and
see if we can get
Closer to the light
at the end
Let our eyes show the fire in
our hearts tonight
Yeah, our eyes show the fire
in our hearts tonight
Let our eyes show the fire
Cause you can't stop the fire
You can't stop the fire
Maybe I'm crazy
Yeah, a little naive
But the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Got a long way to go
But I know, I believe
That the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Oh-oh-oh-oh-oh-oh-oh-oh
You don't have to hide, you
know we've all got scars
The broken we were,
becoming who we are
The proof that it doesn't
matter how we start
We can be more than a spark
Let our eyes show the
fire in our hearts tonight
Yeah, our eyes show the fire
in our hearts tonight
Let our eyes show the fire
Cause you can't stop the fire
You can't stop the fire
Maybe I'm crazy
Yeah, a little naive
But the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Got a long way to go
But I know, I believe
That the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
There's a thin line
Between hoping and believing
A thin line
Between sleeping and dreaming
Between paying dues
And losing everything that
ever mattered to you
Well this is our time
This is our life
This is our song
And this is our night
And if the world gives up
We'll carry on
Turn the volume up
And sing along
Oh-oh-oh-oh
Yeah, you've got a home,
And you've got a song.
Oh-oh-oh-oh
No, you're not alone,
Just sing along.
Oh-oh-oh-oh
Through the ups and downs,
When the road gets long.
Oh-oh-oh-oh
Know you're not alone
Maybe I'm crazy
Yeah, a little naive
But the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Got a long way to go
But I know, I believe
That the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Maybe I'm crazy
Yeah, a little naive
But the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Got a long way to go
But I know, I believe
That the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be
Oh-oh-oh-oh
Got a long way to go
But I know, I believe
That the light at the end is
brighter than it used to be